Peter Lipman-Wulf Papers
Peter Lipman-Wulf Papers
1945-1975
Lipman-Wulf, Peter.
1.25 linear ft.
Spanning 1945 through 1975, the Peter Lipman-Wulf Papers consists of correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the American sculptor, painter, graphic artist and educator (b. 1905). A German Jew by birth, Peter Lipman-Wulf fled to France in 1933 where he was interned in a prison camp before emigrating to the United States in 1947. While documenting his professional career, the collection reveals little of his personal life or war-time experiences.
149504
Biographical History
Peter Lipman-Wulf (1905-1993) was born in Berlin to a prominent lawyer and his wife, a well-known sculptor, and studied at the Berlin Academy. Artistic success came quickly; he took first prize in the Prussian State Competition and had commissions from the city of Berlin for two marble fountains before he was 27 years old.
In 1933 Lipman-Wulf lost his teaching position at the State Academy of Fine Arts in Berlin due to growing anti-Semitism in Nazi Germany and he moved to France. Although he did not declare himself to the French government as a Jew, when France began arresting "enemy aliens" in 1939 he and hundreds of other immigrants were interned at Les Milles near Aix-en-Provence. (He was in sterling company, as his fellow detainees included painter Max Ernst, opera producer Friedrich Schramm, journalist Heinz Bieber-Georgi, two Nobel Prize winners in medicine, and numerous other "undesirables.") In 1940 he volunteered for a work detail in Normandy, from which he managed to escape to Switzerland where he remained through the end of the war.
In 1947 Lipman-Wulf moved to the United States, settling in New York and eventually becoming an American citizen. In addition to his own artistic endeavors he taught at Adelphi University on Long Island.
Lipman-Wulf worked in wood, bronze and ceramics in a semi-abstract style that often reflected the influence of German Expressionism. He also did portrait busts, including those of conductors Bruno Walter and Karl Bohm for the Metropolitan Opera. His work is in the permanent collections of museums and galleries in the United States and abroad, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the National Gallery of Art in Washington, the British Museum in London and the National Museum in Berlin.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from Lipman-Wulf's obituary in the New York Times (September 30, 1993) and from The Holocaust, the French, and the Jews by Susan Zuccotti (University of Nebraska Press: 1999).]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1945 through 1975, the Peter Lipman-Wulf Papers consists of correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the American sculptor, painter, graphic artist and educator (b. 1905). A German Jew by birth, Peter Lipman-Wulf fled to France in 1933 where he was interned in a prison camp before emigrating to the United States in 1947. While documenting his professional career, the collection reveals little of his personal life or war-time experiences.
Correspondence is limited to a few predominantly incoming business letters concerning the creation of Peter Lipman-Wulf's own weekly radio program an New York station WEVD and the manuscripts he submitted for publication in the contemporary art Journal Leonardo.
Writings includes essays, notes, speeches, and radio scripts, the latter constituting the largest portion of the collection. Represented by both holograph and typescript drafts as well as the published versions which appeared in Leonardo, the essays are explications of Lipman-Wulf's artistic creations and principles. Also in this series, a manuscript and outlines of several speeches, as well as miscellaneous notes. Arranged chronologically (1950-1955), the 132 radio scripts for Lipman-Wulf's WEVD program encompass a broad range of art-related essays and Interviews. A broadcast list created by Peter Lipman-Wulf is located at the beginning of the radio scripts.
Memorabilia consists almost exclusively of printed material about Lipman-Wulf, and includes articles, clippings (1964-1965) and exhibition catalogs (1965-1974).
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Art -- Sculptors; Lipman-Wulf, Peter.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Jewish artists -- United States.; German Americans.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Essays.; Exhibition catalogs.; Interviews.; Radio scripts.; Speeches (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Leonardo (publication), 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - WEVD (radio station), 1950 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Essays
    - "Dance in My Sculpture", 1970; manuscript drafts; manuscript, copyedited; reprint from Leonardo, vol. 3 (Box 1)
    - "Joseph and His Brothers", manuscript (holograph) (Box 1)
    - "On My Illustrations of Goethe's 'Faust'", 1975; reprint from Leonardo, vol. 8 (Box 1)
    - "On Teaching a Fundamental Sculpture Course", 1973; manuscript drafts; manuscript copyedited; reprint from Leonardo, vol. 6 (Box 1)
    - "On Teaching Art in America", 1972; manuscript drafts; manuscript; Leonardo, vol. 5 (Box 1)
    - "The Sculptor and the Design", holograph manuscript (Box 1)
    - "Sculpture in Wood", holograph manuscript (Box 1)
    - "Ventures in Precious Books", manuscript (Box 1)
    - "Wall, Space and Sculpture: a Memoir", 1971; research notes; manuscript drafts; manuscript; reprint from Leonardo, vol. 4; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Radio broadcast list, 1950-1955 (Box 2)
  - Radio scripts
    - Radio scripts, 1950; 23 folders (Box 2)
      1950 Mar. 31 "Through the Artist's Looking-glass" - essay
      1950 Apr. 7 "The Art World in Paris" - essay
      1950 Apr. 14 "Modern Art" - essay
      1950 Apr. 21 "Portraiture" - essay
      1950 Apr. 28 "The Vienna Treasures" - essay
      1950 May 5 "Children's Art" - essay
      1950 May 12 "Amateur Art" - essay
      1950 May 19 "Drawing and Design" - essay
      1950 May 26 "With Canvas and Easel on Vacation" - essay
      1950 June 2 "Woman's Art" - essay
      1950 June 9 "Traditional Art and Theater in Oberammergau" - essay
      1950 June 16 "Old and New French Tapestries" - essay
      1950 June 23 "About Chess Sets" - essay
      1950 June 30 "Artist's Balls and Carnivals" - essay
      1950 Nov. 10 "The Artist and the Virgin Islands" - essay
      1950 Nov. 17 "Report from Paris" - essay
      1950 Nov. 24 "Expressionism and Munch" - essay
      1950 Nov. 24 Eric Isenburger - interview
      1950 Dec. 1 Jack D. Wolfe - interview
      1950 Dec. 8 Raymond Frank Piper - interview
      1950 Dec. 15 Marcia Brown - interview
      1950 Dec. 22 "About Art Books" - essay
      1950 Dec. 29 "African Art" - essay
    - Radio scripts, 1951; 23 folders (Box 2)
      1951 Jan. 5 Bernard Constant Meyer - interview
      1951 Jan. 12 re: exhibitions of drawings - essay
      1951 Jan. 19 re: Sculpture Center and Sculptors Guild - essay
      1951 Jan. 26 re: flowers and plants in art - interview
      1951 Feb. 2 Hugh Stix - interview
      1951 Feb. 9 Klaus Gunther Perls - interview
      1951 Feb. 16 "Fashion and Art" - essay
      1951 Feb. 23 Simon Lissim - interview
      1951 Mar. 2 Vladimir Visson - guest essay
      1951 Mar. 9 "Old and New Jewish Art" - essay
      1951 Mar. 23 William Zorach - interview
      1951 Mar. 30 re: watercolor painting - essay
      1951 Apr. 6 Lloyd Goodrich - guest essay
      1951 Apr. 13 re: Horst Janson on Max Beckmann - essay
      1951 Apr. 27 Lena Gurr and Elisabeth Model - interview
      1951 Apr. Elisabeth Kaufmann - interviews
      1951 May 4 John Taylor Arms - interview
      1951 May 11 Hudson D. Walker - interview
      1951 June 1 "Artists Equity Association Building Fund" - essay
      1951 Nov. 7 "First Woodstock Art Film Festival" - essay
      1951 Nov. 14 "A Roundup of Important Exhibitions" - essay
      1951 Dec. 5 Minna Harkavy - interview
      1951 Dec. 12 Vladimir Visson - interview
    - Radio scripts, 1952; 22 folders (Box 2)
      1952 Jan. 2 Dorothy Norman - interview
      1952 Jan. 9 re: "A Condemned Race: Will We See the Last Sculpture Disappear?" - essay
      1952 Jan. 16 re: textile design - interview
      1952 Jan. 23 Lloyd Goodrich - guest essay
      1952 Jan. 30 "Current Exhibitions" - essay
      1952 Feb. 6 Stanley William Hayter - interview
      1952 Feb. 13 Maurice Lavanoux - interview
      1952 Feb. 20 Barse Miller - interview
      1952 Feb. 27 Alberta T. Ellison - interview
      1952 Mar. 5 re: poster art - essay
      1952 Apr. 2 re: lithography - interview
      1952 Apr. 9 Jacob Lawrence - interview
      1952 Apr. 16 Theodore Rousseau - interview
      1952 Apr. 23 Doris Meltzer - interview
      1952 Apr. 30 Antony Tudor - interview
      1952 May 7 Edith Bry - interview
      1952 May 14 John Ferren - interview
      1952 Nov. 21 re: Metropolitan Museum of Art - essay
      1952 Nov. 28 Yeffe Kimball - interview
      1952 Dec. 5 Simon Lissim - interview
      1952 Dec. 12 Vladimir Visson - interview
      1952 Dec. 26 Minna Citron - interview
    - Radio scripts, 1953; 19 folders (Box 3)
      1953 Jan. 9 Julius Carlebach - interview
      1953 Jan. 16 Victor Candell, Colette Roberts, Hugo Robus - interview
      1953 Jan. 22 Samuel M. Adler - interview
      1953 Jan. 26 Arbit Blatas - interview
      1953 Feb. 9 Vladimir Kagan - interview
      1953 Feb. 14 Marcel Vertes - interview
      1953 Feb. 20 John I. Baur - interview
      1953 Feb. 25 George Burton Cumming - interview
      1953 Mar. 6 Lloyd Goodrich - interview
      1953 Mar. 13 Peter Lipman-Wulf - self-interview
      1953 Mar. 26 Mildred Constantine - interview
      1953 Apr. 3 re: Camille Pissarro exhibition - interview
      1953 Apr. 24 Charles Richard Hulbeck - interview
      1953 Apr. Barbara Lekberg - interview
      1953 May 1 re: popularity of ceramics - interview
      1953 Nov. 6 "European Trip 1953" - essay
      1953 Nov. 13 "European Experiences" - essay
      1953 Nov. 20 Andre Racz - interview
      1953 Nov. 27 Lloyd Goodrich - interview, guest essay
      1953 Bunsaku Kurata - interview
    - Radio scripts, 1954; 15 folders (Box 3)
      1954 Jan. 15 John I. Baur, George Grosz - interview
      1954 Feb. 19 re: Andean art - essay
      1954 Feb. 26 re: Metropolitan Museum of Art - essay
      1954 Mar. 5 Simon Lissim - interview
      1954 Mar. 12 re: two exhibitions - essay
      1954 Mar. 19 re: Paul Klee exhibition - essay
      1954 Mar. 26 re: federal grant to the arts - essay
      1954 Apr. 2 Futurisme - essay
      1954 Apr. 16 re: Edouard Vuillard - essay
      1954 Nov. 12 re: "Art Review" radio program - essay
      1954 Nov. 19 re: art public at large - essay
      1954 Nov. 26 Roy and Marie Neuberger - interview
      1954 Dec. 3 Irwin Hersey - interview
      1954 Dec. 17 Dorothy Paris - interview
      1954 Dec. 31 Jacques Zucker - interview
    - Radio scripts, 1955; 11 folders (Box 3)
      1955 Jan. 7 Walter W. S. Cook - interview
      1955 Jan. 14 Salvador Dali - interview
      1955 Jan. 21 Jay Bryan Nash - interview
      1955 Jan. 28 Victor E. d'Amico - interview
      1955 Feb. 4 Adelyn Dohme Breeskin - interview
      1955 Feb. 27 Wendell Phillips - interview
      1955 Feb. Irwin Hersey - interview
      1955 Mar. 11 re: New York Circulating Library of Paintings - interview
      1955 Mar. 18 re: "The Family of Man" - essay
      1955 re: exhibition about teaching art to children - interview
      1955 re: Francisco Goya - essay
    - Radio scripts, undated; 18 folders (Box 3)
      re: William Blake and Henry Fuseli - essay
      Julius Carlebach - interview
      Hans Curjel - interview
      The Economic State of the Artists - essay
      An Exhibition at the Pierpont Morgan Library - essay
      Sidney Janis - interview
      Pupul Jayakar - interview
      Ethel Katz - interview
      Fernand Leger - essay
      Henri Matisse - essay
      re: museums - essay
      re: Pablo Picasso - essay
      re: public interest in art museums - interview
      Rodin - essay
      Three Kings - essay
      Van Gogh - essay
      Alfred Werner - interview
      Charles White - interview
  - Speeches
    - "Contemporary Sculpture in the Light of Our Technology, Our Social and Economic Needs", undated; drafts, manuscript (Box 3)
    - re: modern art - Oakland, Aug. 1952; outline (Box 3)
    - "Trends in American Art" - New World Club, 11 Nov. 1951; outline (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 7 holograph pages (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Printed material
    - Articles about, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Clippings about, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs, announcements, 1965-1974 (Box 3)
    - Publicity for "Dies Irae", 1963 (Box 3)
    - Miscellany, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Miscellany
    - List of benefit exhibitions, 1945-1950 (Box 3)